OK, good morning.
早上好
So today we are going to, as I mentioned last week,
正如我上周提到过的 今天我们要讲的是...
we've started the part of the course where we are doing more
我们最近这一部分课程的内容
things having to do with design than purely analysis.
将涉及到更多设计上的内容 而不是纯粹的分析
Today, we're actually going to do analysis,
虽然 今天我们还要做分析
but it's the type of analysis
但这种分析
that leads to really interesting design issues.
会涉及到非常有趣的设计内容
And we're going to follow it up on Wednesday
接下来 在周三的课上
with an application of the methods we're going to learn today
我们会运用到今天将要学到的一种方法
with a really interesting and practical problem.
来解决一个相当有趣而且实际的问题
So we're talking today about amortized analysis.
那么 今天要讲的是平摊分析
And I want to motivate this topic by asking the question,
我打算通过提问来引出主题
how large should a hash table be?
一个哈希表多大才合适？
So, how large should a hash table be? Any suggestions?
一个哈希表多大才合适？有什么建议？
You have got to make a hash table, how big should I make it?
如果要建立一个哈希表 应该设定为多大？
Let's say it's a simple hash table,
假设要建立一个简单哈希表
resolving collisions with chaining.
用链接法来解决冲突
How big should it be?
它要多大才合适？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Twice as big as you need:
[教授]：两倍你所需要大小
OK, how big would that be?
那是多大？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:So, twice the number of elements, for example,
[教授]：举个例子 要元素数量的两倍大
OK. As I increase the size of a hash table,
那么 当我增大哈希表时
what happens to the search time?
搜索时间会发生什么变化？
What happens to search time
当我增加哈希表的大小时
as I increase the size of the hash table?
搜索时间会怎么变化？
Yeah, but what does it, in general do?
对 但通常会怎么变化
It decreases, right?
会减小 是吧？
OK, the bigger I make it,
哈希表越大...
in fact, if I make it sufficiently large,
实际上 如果设为足够大
then I essentially get a direct access table,
那就会得到一个直接映射表
and everything is worst-case, order one time.
在最坏情况下 时间为 O（1）
So in some sense,
所以在某种程度上
we'll get back to your answer in a minute.
等下再说说你的答案
We should make it as large as possible,
我们应该让它越大越好
OK, so that the searching is cheap.
这样搜索时间就会很少
The flipside of that is what?
这样做的缺陷是什么？
It takes a lot of space
这样需要很大的空间
so I should make it as small as possible
所以哈希表又应该尽可能地小
so as not to waste space.
这样才不至于浪费太多空间
So I want it big,
但我又希望它能大一点
and the happy medium, as we've discussed in our analysis,
正如在分析中讨论过的那样
is to make it order n size for n items,
对于n个项 最好的折中值的是θ(n)
OK, because making it larger than order n,
因为如果哈希表的体积超过θ(n)
the payoff in search time is not worth
就不值得为了减少那点搜索时间
the extra amount of space that you are paying.
去增加额外的空间了
OK, or at least you can view it that way.
或者至少你能这样理解
However, this begs the question, which is, how do I make it,
然而 还有个问题 那就是如何建立哈希表
if I start out with a hash table, and I don't know
如果创建哈希表时 我并不知道...
how many elements are going to be hashed into it?
有多少个元素将要加进来
OK, how big should I make it?
那哈希表的大小应该设为多少？
OK, so what if we don't know in advance?
如果在不知道n的前提下
OK, what if we don't know n?
如果n是未知的话？
OK, so the solution to this problem turns out
这个问题的解法是这样的
it's fairly elegant. It's a strategy called dynamic tables.
这个策略很优美 它叫做动态表
OK, and the idea is that
它的思想是
whenever the table gets too many elements in it,
当哈希表里映射进了太多元素时
gets too full,
被挤爆了
OK, so the idea is
解决方法是
OK, and we say that says the table overflows,
我们称这个表“溢出”了
OK, we grow it and make a bigger table.
那么就增大它 把表弄得更大
So, for hashing, although there's going to be no point
对于哈希 尽管没有证据表明...
at which you could say that
我们并不能断定
it overflows in the sense that it wouldn't be functional
哈希表的溢出会导致它失效
at least if it was done with chaining.
至少用链接法时 它不会失效
There would be, by the way,
但也是有这种可能
if you were doing it with open addressing.
如果你用的是公开寻址法的话
But let's say with chaining, when it gets too big,
在使用链接法的情况下 当元素变得太多时
say, as many elements as the size of the table,
例如 当元素数量等于表的大小时
what we do is we grow the table.
我们就要增大表的大小
So, the way we do that as we allocate
要分配一个更大的表
using in a language like C, it's called Malloc,
例如在C语言中 我们用malloc()
or in a language like Java called New, a larger table.
或者在Java中 用new来建更大的表
So, we create a larger table.
这样 新建一个更大的表
We move the items from the old table to the new.
将项从旧的表移到新的表
And then, we free the old table.
然后释放旧表的空间
So, let's do an example.
举一个例子
So, let's say I have, over here, a table of size one,
假设在这里有一个大小为1的表
and it's empty to begin with.
一开始它是空的
And I do an insert.
我做一个插入操作
So what I do is stick it in the table. It fits.
把元素放进表里 刚好满了
OK, so here, I'm not going to do it with hashing.
这里不做具体的哈希过程
I'm just going to do it as if I just had a table that
直接放进去 就像是我有一个表
I was filling up with elements to abstract the problem.
然后我把它装满了 把问题抽象化
But it would work with hashing.
当然用哈希也行
It would work with any kind of fixed size data structure.
对于任意固定大小的数据结构而言 都是可行的
I insert again, oops, doesn't fit.
我再进行插入 噢 这下不行
I get an overflow.
它溢出了
OK, so what I do is I create a new,
这时要新建一个表
actually, I'm going to need a little more space than that.
实际上 我要画得再紧凑点
I create a new table of size two, doubling the size.
我新建一个大小为2的表 两倍于原来的大小
And, I copy the old value into the new.
然后将旧的值复制到新表中
I freed this one, and now I can insert item two.
再释放旧表的空间 现在我能插入第二项了
So, I do it again. I get another overflow.
再进行插入 又得到一个溢出
So now, I make a table of size four.
现在我新建一个大小为4的表
I copied these guys in, and then I insert my number three.
将这些项复制进去 然后插入第三个数
I do insert here. I do five.
继续插入到这里 然后是第五项
I guess I should be using ditto marks.
这里写个“同上”算了
That would be a lot smarter.
这样会方便很多
Whoops, what am I doing? I overflow.
噢 我做了什么 又溢出了
And now, I make one of size eight,
再建造一个表大小为8
OK, copy these over, and now I can insert five.
把这些复制过去 然后就能插入第五项了
And I can do six, seven, etc.,
同样地 插入第六项 第七项等等
OK? Does everybody understand the basic idea?
大家都理解了这个基本思路了吗？
So, whenever I overflow,
一旦发生溢出
I'm going to create a table of twice the size.
新建一个两倍于原大小的表
OK, so let's do a quick analysis of this.
对这个方法做一个快速的分析
So, we have a sequence of n insertion operations.
有一个序列 包括n个插入运算
OK, what is the worst-case cost of one insert operation?
在最坏情况下 一次插入运算的代价是多少？
What's the worst case for any one of these?
对于任意项 它的最坏情况是什么？
Yeah, it's order n, whatever the overhead is of copying;
没错 是θ(n) 无论复制的开销是多少
if we counted it as one,
如果一步复制算为1
it would be basically n or n plus one
这些复制操作的时间是n或者是n+1
because we've got to copy all those.
因为要把所有项复制过来
OK, so it's order n.
所以是θ(n)
So therefore, if I have n of those,
因此 如果有n个项
so the worst-case cost of n inserts
最坏情况下 n个插入运算的代价
is equal to n times order n,
为n·θ(n)
which is order n^2.
也就是θ(n^2)
Any questions?
有什么问题吗？
Does that make sense?
带感不？
Raise hands.
举手示意一下
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Yeah, not all of them can be worst-case, good.
[教授]：不是所有的项都是最坏情况 非常好
And in fact, this is totally wrong analysis.
实际上 这是完全错误的分析
Just because one can be worst-case order n
因为一个项在最坏情况下是θ(n)
doesn't mean n are necessarily order n.
并不代表n个项都是θ(n)
OK, so this is totally wrong analysis.
所以这是个完全错误的分析
n inserts, in fact, take order n time in the worst case.
实际上在最坏情况下 n个插入花费θ(n)的时间
OK, it doesn't take order n^2.
不是θ(n^2)
So, the analysis is correct up to the point
这个分析到这一步还是正确的
where we set the worst-case of one insert was order n.
设最坏情况下 一次插入的时间为θ(n)
Therefore, that's the wrong step.
所以 出错的是这一步
OK, whenever you see bugs in proofs, you want to know,
当你发现证明有错误时
which step is the one that failed
你要知道是在哪一步出错的
so you can make sure that you don't
这样人家才..才不会...
have a confusion there?
才不会感到困惑呢
So, let's do the proper analysis,
那么 我们做一次正确的分析
OK? So let's let c_i be the cost of the i'th insert.
设c_i为第i个插入的代价
OK, so that's equal to i,
那么 c_i将等于i
if i minus one is an exact power of two.
当 i-1 为2的幂时
And it's one otherwise.
否则c_i等于1
OK, so as I was going through here,
正如这里讲的一样
it was only when I inserted something
只有当插入之前
where the previous one had been the exact power of two,
已经刚好有2的幂个元素
because that was my table size.
因为这是表的大小
That's when I got the overflow
所以我遇到溢出
and had to do all that copying.
必须全部进行复制
And otherwise, the cost, for example,
其余情况下的代价是
for inserting six, was just one.
比如插入第六项的代价为1
I just inserted it.
只需插入运算
Does everybody see that?
大家都理解吗？
So, let's actually make a little table here
在这里画一个小列表
so we can see this a little bit more clearly.
这样我们能看得更明白
OK, so here's i,
这里是i
and in the size of the table at step i,
第i步时表的大小
and the cost at step i.
这是第i步的代价
OK, so let's see, the size of i,
这是第i步表的大小
let's see, at step one it was one.
第1步时表的大小是1
At step two, it was two.
第2步是2
And at step three,
在第3步
that's when, to get three in the table,
当要在表里插入第3项时
we had to double the size here.
必须先将表的大小翻倍
So, this is four, and four, it fit.
所以这里是4 接下来是第4项 没问题
And then five, it had to bump up to eight.
然后是第5项 表必须增大到8
And then, six, it was eight.
然后是第6项 大小仍是8
Seven, it was eight. Eight, it was eight.
第7项是8 第8项是8
And nine, it bumps up to 16, 16, etc.
第9项 增加到16 以此类推
So that's the size.
这些是表的大小
And let's take a look at what the cost was.
看一下时间代价是多少
So, the cost here was one,
这里代价为1
OK, to insert one.
插入第1项
The cost here was, I had to copy one,
这里的代价是 要复制1个项
and then insert one.
然后再插入1项
So, the cost was two.
所以代价是2
Here, I had to copy two and insert one.
这里 要复制2项再插入1项
So, the cost was three.
所以代价是3
Here, I had to just insert one.
这里只需要插入1项
So, the cost was one.
所以代价是1
Here, I had to copy four and insert one.
这里要复制4项再插入1项
So, the cost was five.
所以代价是5
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Excuse me? I think it is.
[教授]：再说一遍？应该没错
Yeah, see, it's i.
没错 看 这是i
The cost for five is i,
第5项的代价是i
OK, is five if this is a power of two.
也就是5 如果之前的大小刚好为2的幂
OK, one, one, and now we paid nine, and then one again.
这些都是1 这一项代价为9 最后又是1
So that's the cost we are paying.
这些是付出的时间代价
It's a little bit easier to see
这样具体到每一步
what the costs are if I break them down.
时间代价看起来 更加清晰易懂
OK, so let's just redraw this as two values
好 把c_i分成两部分来表示
because there is always the cost for inserting
因为这里总有插入的那一项
the one thing that I want to insert.
所需的时间代价
And now, the residual amount that I have to pay is
剩余的这些时间代价
I have to pay one here.
这里花费1
I've got to pay two additional,
这里要多花费2
four additional, eight additional.
加4 加8
That makes the pattern a little bit easier to see.
这样整个模式看起来更容易理解
OK, this is the cost of copying versus
这些是复制的时间代价
the cost of just doing the actual insert, OK?
上面这行只是插入的时间代价
Now, if you're taking notes, leave some space here
如果你现在在做笔记 在这里留点空间
because I'm going to come back to this table later.
因为等下还要再回来讲一下这个表
OK, so leave a little bit of space
所以 预留一点空间
because I'm going to come back
因为等下还会回来
and add some more things at there at a later time.
这里还要再讲多一些东西
OK, so, I can then just add up the cost of n inserts.
将n个插入项的代价加起来
That's just the sum, I equals one to n of c_i,
求总和 i从1到n
which is equal to,
它等于
well, by this analysis it is essentially n
由上述分析得到 它等于n...
because that's what this thing adds up to
也就是这些1加起来
plus I just have to add the powers of two up to
再加上 这些2的幂
but not exceeding whatever my n was.
但它们的上限不超过n
So, if I do my algebra properly there,
如果我没算错的话
that's up to the floor of log n minus one,
这里是到log(n-1)的整数最小值
OK, of two to the J.
2的j次幂的总和
So, I'm just adding up all the powers of two up to
将上限不会超过n的
that aren't going to exceed my n.
所有2的幂加起来
And, this is what type of series?
这是什么类型的数列
That's geometric.
这是几何级数
That's geometric, so it is bounded by its largest term.
所以 它的上界被最大项控制
Its largest term is two to the ceiling;
它的最大项是 2的这个上限次幂
it's dominated by its largest term,
它由这个的最大项控制
two to the ceiling of log n minus one, which is, at most, n.
2的log(n-1)次幂 即最大值为n
OK, and then all the other terms at up to, at most, n.
然后 其它所有项的上限也是不超过n
So this is actually less than or equal to 3n,
所以最后小于或等于3n
which is order n as we want it to show.
也就是θ(n) 如所欲证
OK, that's algebra.
这是代数运算
OK, so, thus, the average cost per insert
所以每个插入运算的平均代价
is theta of n over n, which is theta one.
等于θ(n)/n 也就是θ(1)
So, the average cost of an insert is order one,
一个插入的平均代价是θ(1)
which is what we would like it to be
这是我们想要的结果
especially if we're building hash tables.
特别是当我们在创建哈希表时
Even though sometimes you have to pay a big price
尽管有时候要付出比较大的代价
with amortized, that big expense,
但这个巨大的开销
over the previous insertions that we've done,
会被之前的插入平摊掉
so that the overall cost of n operations is order n.
因此n个操作的总代价是θ(n)
And that's the notion of amortized analysis,
这就是平摊分析的思想
OK, that if I look at a sequence of operations,
如果看到一个操作序列
I can spread the cost out over a whole bunch of operations,
我可以将时间代价平摊到所有操作上
so that the average cost is order n.
这样平均的代价是θ(n)
So, if we sort of summarize that, OK,
总结一下
OK, with basically an amortized analysis,
用平摊分析
we analyze a sequence of operations
来分析一个操作序列
to show that the average cost per operation is small,
证明每个操作的平均代价很小
even though one operation, or several,
尽管一个或多个操作
even, may be expensive.
可能代价很大
OK, there's no probability.
这里没有涉及到概率
Even though we're doing it with averages,
尽管我们用到了平均
there's no probability going on.
但并没有涉及到概率学
OK, what you do probability,
当涉及概率学时
and you are looking at means, there's averages.
我们会用到期望值 即平均值
OK, here's another average,
但这是另一种平均值
but there's no probability going on.
但没有涉及概率学
It's average performance in the worst case
它是最坏情况下的平均表现
because n operations take me
n个操作的代价
a constant amount of time per operation in the worst case.
在最坏情况下 平均起来每步只是常数
n operations take me order n time.
n个操作花费θ(n)的时间
OK, each operation takes order one time,
每个操作花费θ(1)的时间
OK, but it's amortized over the n operations,
只是平摊到了n个操作上
OK? Yeah, question?
有问题？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Yes. Yes, yes, you can mix,
[教授]：对 没错 可以这样做
but you don't have to.
但没有必要
Yeah, but the point is that the basic amortized analysis
重点是 基础的平摊分析
is actually saying something very strong.
实际上 它能给出非常强的结果
It's giving you worst-case bounds,
它给出的是最坏情况的代价上限
but over a sequence
但这是一整个操作序列的上限
as opposed to looking at each individual element of the sequence.
而不是序列里的每一个单独元素的上限
Now, there are three types of amortized arguments
现在有三种类型的平摊方法
that appear in the literature.
都是在文献上出现过的
Maybe there are more.
也可能有更多类型
At one point, there were two.
以前只有两种
And then, a third one was developed.
后来发明了第三种
So, maybe there's a fourth.
所以 可能会有第四种
The first one is an aggregate,
第一种是聚集
what's called an aggregate analysis.
称为聚集分析
And this is what we just saw,
也就是我们刚才看到的
OK, where basically you just analyze,
基本上就是要你分析
what do the n operations take?
n次操作花费一共花多少时间？
OK, and then we're going to see two more today.
今天要介绍另外两种方法
One is called an accounting argument,
一种叫做记账方法
and the other is a potential argument.
另一种叫做势能方法
These two are more precise, because they
这两种更精确 因为它们...
they allocate specific amortized costs to each operation.
它们为每一个操作分配了特定的平摊代价
So, one of the things about the aggregate analysis is that
关于聚集分析 有一点要说明的是
you can't really say what the amortized cost
你不能轻易地确定一个单独操作...
of a single operation is easily.
它的平摊代价具体是多少
You can in this case.
但这种情况可以
You can say it's order one,
你可以说它是θ(1)
But, in the accounting and potential arguments,
但在记账和势能方法里
it gives you a much more precise way of characterizing
给出一种更加精确的方法
what an amortized cost of a particular operation is.
来表示一个特定操作的平摊代价是多少
So, let's pitch in and look at
我们来看一下
the accounting method as our first method.
第一个要看的方法是记账方法
So, these we're going to go through the exact same example.
用这个方法再走一遍与之前完全相同的例子
In some sense, this example, the easiest argument to make
在某种程度上 这个例子最简单的分析方案
is the aggregate analysis.
是聚集分析
OK, so we're going get into arguments that,
也就是说 我们将要用到的另一个方法
in some sense, see more complicated.
从某种程度来看 它更复杂
But it turns out that these methods are more powerful
但实际上 这两种方法其实更加强大
in many circumstances.
在大部分情况下
OK, and so I want to do it in a simple situation
所以 我想在一个简单的情况下做一次
where you have some sort of appreciation
这样你就应该意识到
of the fact that you can look at any particular problem
对于任意一个特定的问题
and approach it from different ways.
你都能用不同的方法来完成它
OK, so the accounting method is
好的 记账方法是
putting yourself in the position of a financial accountant.
设想自己担任了一个财务会计的职位
So what you do is we are going to charge the i'th operation
你要做的就是对第i个操作“收费”
a fictitious amortized cost.
收一个虚构的平摊代价
We'll call it c hat sub i,
称之为c^i
where we are going to use the abstraction that
将时间代价看作是
$1 pays for one unit of work.
每一步运算要花费1美元
There's time manipulating the data structure or whatever.
因为要花时间来处理数据结构
OK, so the idea is you charge the cost.
所以 你要向操作收费
You say, this operation will cost you $5 or whatever.
比如这个操作将花费你5美元左右
And that fee is consumed to perform the operation,
这份费用是支付给这个操作的
but there may be some unused part.
但可能还剩下一些用剩下的
So, if there's any unused amount,
那么 如果还有未用到的余款
it's going to be stored in the bank
它将存放在银行里
for use by later operations.
用于偿付以后的操作
So the idea is that if the fee that is being paid,
如果第i次给的费用...
the c_i hat fee,
费用c^i
isn't sufficient to pay for performing the operation,
不足以给支付成这些操作
then you take money out of the bank to pay for it.
那么就从银行里取出钱来付款
and so you don't get arrested,
这样你才不会被关小黑屋
what's the property that you've got to have?
你需要多少财产才够呢？
You've got to have the bank balance.
你需要有一些银行存款余额
What about the bank balance?
存款余额要有多少？
What mathematical fact has to hold the bank balance?
银行存款是多少才符合数学逻辑?
Yeah, it better be greater than or equal to zero, right?
这还用说 它应该大于或等于0吧?
Most people are familiar with that.
大家都懂的
So, the bank balance must not go negative.
存款余额不能是负数
In other words, the amortized costs
换句话说 到这一步操作之前
minus the costs of the operations up to that point
所有的平摊代价减去操作代价的余额
have to always be enough to pay
必须总是足够偿付
for all the operations that you're doing.
当前所有操作的花费
Otherwise, you're borrowing on the future.
否则 你就是在向未来借款了
In amortized analysis, we don't borrow on the future,
在平摊分析里 不能向未来借款
at least not on the simple ones that we are doing here.
至少在这里这个简单的例子里不能
So that means we must have that the sum,
这意味着有这个总和
I equals one to n of c_i, the true costs,
c_i从1到n求和 这是实际代价
therefore, if the balance is not going to ever go negative,
因此 如果存款不会变为负数
must be bounded above by the amortized costs for all n.
则必须小于或等于 n次操作的平摊代价的总和
OK, for the bank balance not to go negative,
为了存款余额不会变为负数
if I add up the true costs,
如果合计所有实际代价
it's got to be the case that I can always pay for them.
那么存款总是足以偿付实际代价
If I am only charging, this is what I'm charging.
如果我要收费的话 这就是我收取的费用
This is what it actually costs me.
而这个 是实际的花费
So, it better be the case that
所以应该是这种情形
whatever I've actually had to pay
无论实际需要花费多少
to operate on that data structure,
来运作这个数据结构
that's what this is,
也就是这个实际花费
better be covered by the amount that
它应该足以被
I've been charging people
我所收取的费用来偿付
for the use of that data structure up to that point.
也就是之前这个数据结构的使用费
And that's got to be true for all n.
这对于所有的n都是成立的
But notice that this now gives me a way
注意到 现在这种方法
of charging a particular operation a certain amount.
可以给某个特定的操作 收取一定量的费用
So, the total amortized costs provide an upper bound
所以 总的平摊代价为总的实际代价
on the total true costs.
提供了一个上限
Total amortized costs are an upper bound on the true costs.
总的平摊代价是实际代价的上限
Any question about this?
对于这个有什么问题吗？
That we'll do the example of the dynamic table
我们会在动态表上用这种方法
using this methodology.
来做一个例子
So, back to the dynamic table.
回到动态表
OK, so what we're going to do in this case is
在这个例子里 我们所要做的是
we're going to charge an amortized cost of $3
收取3美元的平摊费用
for the i'th insert for all i.
作为所有的第i步操作的费用
And the idea is that
收费标准是
$1 is going to pay for an immediate insert,
1美元付给一个即时插入
and $2 is going to be stored for doubling the table.
还有2美元用于将表翻倍的预存费用
And, it needs to be expanded.
因为表需要扩增
When the table doubles, we use the stored dollars,
当表的大小增加一倍时
we'll use one dollar to move a recent item, I'll call it,
我们就从存款里 取出1美元来移动新项
and one dollar we'll move an old item.
还有1美元用来移动旧项
So, let's do the example.
我们做个例子
So, imagine that I'm in this situation
假设我们的情况是
where I have a table of size eight,
有一个大小为8的表
and I just doubled my table.
而且我刚刚才表翻倍
So I have four items of the table.
所以表里有4个项
What I'm going to do is have no dollars in my table.
然后这个表里已经没有美元剩下了
So, along comes an insertion of item number five.
接下来要进行第5项的插入操作
I charge $3 for it.
为此收取3美元
$1 lets me put the item in the table,
用1美元 将项插入到表里
and I have $2 left over.
还剩下2美元
So let me store those $2 in the slot
将这2美元存放在槽里
corresponding to where that item is.
相对于这个项的所在位置
Now, item six comes in.
现在第6项来了
Once again, $1, charge $3,
再一次 收取3美元
$1 is paid for the insert,
1美元付给插入运算
$2 left over, I'm going to play $2.
还剩2美元 将2美元存起来
Let me put it down there, and so forth.
将它放在这里 然后继续
The next one comes in, $2, $2 leftover,
下一个又来了 这里是2美元 还剩下2美元
and now the ninth item comes in.
直到第9项来了
So, I double the size of my table.
我要将表的大小增大为一倍
OK, and now I copy all of these guys
然后 我要将所有这些项
into all of these here.
复制进新表里
And what happens?
会发生什么？
Look at that: I've got $8,
看这里 我有8美元
and I've got eight items that have to be copied.
而我又有8个项需要复制
Perfect.
刚好
OK, so one of these dollars pays for
所以其中的1美元付给
one of the ones that was inserted in the last round,
在最新一轮里插进来的那项
and one of them pays for an old one.
还有1美元付给一个旧的项
OK, and so, I copy them in,
将它们复制进来
and now, none of those guys have any money.
现在这些槽里都没有存款了
And the ninth guy comes in: he has $2 left over.
第9项进来了 剩余2美元
And then, we keep going on.
然后 继续这些步骤
OK, so you see that by that argument,
通过这个方法
I can say that if I charge everybody $3,
如果向每个人收取3美元
OK, I can always handle all of the table doubling,
我总是能偿付所有表扩增的花费
the charges for the table doubling
存款用于表的扩增
because the inductive invariant that I've maintained is that
因为我维持了一个归纳不变量
after it doubles, there's nothing in the bank account.
在表扩增后 银行存款就归零了
And now, I put in $2.
现在再放2美元进去
Well then, I can pay,
然后足够偿付了
and I'm now left in the same situation.
剩下的情况是一样的
and it's the case that the bank balance never goes negative.
这种情况下 银行存款余额永不为负
So that's a really important invariant to verify.
所以这是一个相当重要的不变量 我们需要验证一下
And so, therefore, the sum of the true costs,
因此 实际代价的总和
or the amortized costs, upper bound the sum of the true costs.
或者说平摊代价总和 是为实际代价总和的上限
And, since the sum of the amortized cost, here, is,
因为平摊代价的总和
if I go i equals one to n,
这里i是从1到n
OK, this is 3n.
这是3n
So, the point is,
关键在于
now I bounded the sum of the true costs by 3n.
实际代价的上限也就是3n
So let's go back to this table here,
回到这里这个表
and look to see what happens,
看一下是什么情况
OK, if I put in c_i hat, and the bank balance.
如果加入c^i 还有银行存款余额
So in fact, so the first thing I do is insert;
第一步要做的插入操作
I charge $3, right,
收取3美元
and I do an insert.
然后我进行插入
How much do I have left?
还剩余多少？
I'm going to have $2.
剩下2美元
It turns out I'm actually going to charge $2
但实际上 我只要收取2美元
and have only $1 left.
然后剩下1美元
OK, so I'm actually going to under charge the first guy.
实际上 我要给第1项收得便宜些
I'm going to show you that it works if I charge everybody $3.
我会证明 每一项都收取3美元是可行的
Except the first guy: I charge $2.
除了第一项 收取2美元
I can actually save a little bit on number one.
实际上 在第1项可以省1美元
Then, for this guy I'm going to charge $3.
接着这一项 我要收取3美元
OK, what's the size of my bank balance when I'm done?
这样完成后银行存款余额是多少？
Well, I have to copy one guy.
我还要复制1项
He's all paid for, so I have $2 left.
但这个已经付完了 所以还剩下2美元
OK, people with me?
大家都明白吗？
OK, the next guy: I charge $3.
下一个 收取3美元
Actually, I'm going to charge all these guys $3.
实际上 所有这些项都要收取3美元
So here now I basically get to,
到这里我已经有了...
I've got a table of size four.
有一个大小为4的表
So, I basically have, I have to copy,
所以 这里要进行复制
oh, when I insert the third guy, I've got to copy two guys.
当插入第3项时 必须要复制2个
That'll use up that,
这部分存款会用掉
so I'll have only $2 left in the table after I've inserted him.
所以 在插入第三项后 表里只剩下2美元
Now I insert the fourth guy,
现在插入第4项
OK, and that's a good one because
这一步比较简单
now I've built up a balance here of $4
现在这里的存款为4美元
because I didn't have to copy anybody.
因为不用复制任何项
OK, now I insert the fifth guy.
现在插入第5项
I've got to copy four items.
需要复制4项
So that expends that balance.
这样一来存款都要花掉
I have, then, two left.
然后又剩余2美元
OK, and then here basically I add two to it....
然后这里再加2美元 再加...
And then at this point, I use it all up
在这里又全部用掉
and go back to two, etc.
又回到2美元 以此类推
So you see one of the things I want you to notice is
你们需要注意的一点是
I could have charged three here.
这里可以收取3美元
And then I would've had an extra dollar lying around
然后一直会有多余的1美元
throughout here. It wouldn't have mattered.
贯穿整个过程 但它不会有影响
It still would be upper bounded by 3n.
上限仍然是3n
So the idea is that
这里的想法是
different schemes for charging amortized costs can work.
平摊的方案有不同 也是可行的
They don't all have to be the same.
它们没必要都一样
It's not like when you do in amortized analysis that
当你进行平摊分析时
there is one scheme that will work.
它并不是只有一种可行的方案
I could have charged $4 to everybody.
我也可以向每一项都收取4美元
And it would have worked. But it turns out,
这也是可行的 但有一种例外
I couldn't have charged two dollars for everybody.
不能向每一项都收取2美元
If I charged $2 for everybody,
如果每一项都收取2美元
my balance would go negative, OK?
存款余额就会变为负的
My balance would go negative,
余额将是负数
but I can charge three dollars, and that will work.
但可以收取3美元 这是可行的
OK, four, five, six, I could charge that.
同样的也可以收取4，5，6美元
The bound that I would get would be simply a looser bound.
只是会得到一个相对宽松的上限
Instead of it being less than or equal to 3n,
而不是小于或等于3n
it would be less than or equal to 4n or 5n, or what have you.
它将是小于或等于4n或5n 或是其它的
But if I tried to do 2n, it wouldn't have worked
但如果试一下2n 会发现是不可行的
because I wouldn't have enough money left to copy everything.
因为剩余的存款 不够用来进行复制操作
What would happen is I would have only $1 in this,
如果这里只收取1美元 会发生什么情况？
and then when it came time to table double,
当表需要扩增的时候
I would need to copy eight guys.
我需要复制8项
And I'd only have built up a bank account of $4,
但我只有4美元的银行存款
sorry, if I charged $2 and had $1 left over.
抱歉口误了 是如果收取2美元 只剩1美元
So to actually make these things work out,
所以为了让这些方案可行
you have to play a little bit,
你必须多尝试一些
OK, see what works, see what doesn't work.
看一下哪些是可行的 哪些是不可行的
OK, no algorithmic formulas for algorithm design.
不需要算法公式的算法设计
OK, good. In the book,
在课本里
you can read about table contraction.
你可以学一下表压缩
What happens when you start deleting elements?
当删除元素时又会是什么情况？
Now you want to make the table be smaller.
如果想让表更小一些
Now, you have to be very careful because unless you put,
你就必须非常小心 因为除非你放...
who remembers from physics, hysteresis?
有谁还记得物理的磁滞现象
Vaguely? A couple people?
大概记得就行 有谁记得吗？
OK, you have to worry about hysteresis.
必须考虑一下磁滞现象
OK, if you're not careful,
如果你不小心
if whenever it gets to be less than a power of two,
当表小于2的幂时
you go in the half, you can find that you're thrashing.
当进行到一半时 你会发现会系统会颠簸
So, you need to make it so that
所以 你要设计成
there is some memory in the system so that you only collapse
系统先预留一些内存 在完成一定量的删除操作后
after you've done a sufficient number of deletions,
才真正地把内存释放掉
OK, and so forth.
以此类推
And the book has analysis of the more general case.
课本也有对更普遍情况的分析
OK, so any questions about the accounting method?
对于记帐方法还有什么问题没有？
Accounting method is really very cute,
记帐方法真的很有爱
Very cute.
非常有爱
And, it's the one most students prefer to do.
也是大部分学生比较倾向的一种类型
They usually hate the next one until they learn it.
他们通常讨厌将要学习的东西 直到学会它
Once they learn it, they say, ooh, that's cool.
一旦学会了 他们会说 酷炫啊
OK, but to start out with,
但要开始新的学习
it takes a little bit more intestinal fortitude.
就需要一点点勇气
But it's amazing.
但它是神奇的
Good potential arguments are really sweet.
好的势能方法 就像初恋一样难以忘怀
And we are going to see one next time,
下次课我们就会看到一个
so you'll definitely want to review
所以你绝对要复习
and make sure you understand it before Wednesday's lecture
确保在周三的课前你能理解它
because Wednesday's lecture, we're going to assume
因为在周三的课上 我们会假设
we understand potential method.
大家都已经掌握了势能方法
So let's do, enough advertisement.
开始吧 够多广告了
I think the potential method is one of the
我认为势能方法是
beautiful results in algorithmic analysis,
算法分析里最漂亮的产物之一
just beautiful result,
漂亮的产物
beautiful set of techniques.
美妙的技巧集合
and it's also, just in terms of, I mean,
让我组织一下语言
what do you aspire: to be a bookkeeper or to be a physicist?
你是想数一辈子钱呢  还是做个物理学家去改变世界
So, the idea is we don't want to be bankers.
那意思就是 我们都不想做银行家
We want to be physicists.
我们都想做物理学家
And so, this bank account, we are going to say about
因此 银行存款帐户 将变成我们要说到的
the potential energy of the dynamics set that we are analyzing.
要分析的动态集的势能
So, because, why?
为什么？
It delivers up work just like a spring does, for example,
打个比方 它就像弹簧一样做功
OK, when you study potential energy,
当你学习势能的时候
or putting something up high and having gravity pull it down.
或者把某个东西放高 让重力将它拉下来
We convert dynamic to potential,
实际是将动能转为势能
and that's exactly what we're going to be doing here,
这也正是我们在这里要做的事
and it's similar mathematics except that
它在数学上很相似
in our case it turns out to be discrete mathematics
只是在这种情况下用的是离散数学
rather than continuous math for most of it.
而不是在通常所用的连续数学
So here's the framework for the potential method.
好的 这是势能方法的框架
So, we start with some data structure, D_0,
我们由数据结构D_0开始讲起
and operation i transforms D_(i - 1) into D_i.
操作i将D_(i - 1)转化为D_i
So, we view the operation on the data structure as a mapping,
把数据结构上的操作看成是一种映射
mapping one data structure to another data structure,
从一个数据结构映射到另一个数据结构
the one from before to the one after.
从之前那个变成之后那个
OK, already it's nicely mathematical.
这已经是很了不起的数学了
And of course, the costs of operation i remains at c_i.
当然 操作i的操作代价还是c_i
And, now what we are going to do
现在我们要做的是
is define the potential function, phi,
定义势能函数Φ
which maps the set of data structures into the reals.
将数据结构集映射为实数
So, associated with every data structure,
这样就把每个数据结构...
now, is a potential,
跟势关联起来
OK, a real-valued potential,
一种实数值的势
often integer potential
虽然一般势值都是整数
such that phi of D_0 is equal to zero.
这样Φ(D_0)就等于0
So, the initial potential is zero,
初始的势为0
and phi of D_i is greater than or equal to zero for all i.
对于所有i  Φ(D_i)大于或等于0
So, potential can never be nonnegative,
势能不可能为负值
just like the bank account because
正如银行存款一样
the potential is essentially representing the bank account,
因为银行存款也可以表示成势
if you will, in the accounting method.
如果你愿意 大可以在记账方法里试下
OK, so we always want the potential to be nonnegative.
所以我们要让势总不为负
Now, actually,
实际上
there are times where you use potential functions
当你使用势能函数时
where you violate both of these properties.
有时会违反这些性质
There's some really interesting potential arguments
但有一些相当有意思的势能参数
which don't violate like these,
它们不会违反这些性质的
but for the simple ones we're going to be doing in this class,
但像我们在课上用到的这些简单一点的
we'll just assume that these tend to be true.
我们就都假设它们都是成立的
But we will actually see some times where
但实际上你会经常看到
phi of D_0 isn't zero, it doesn't matter.
Φ(D_0)不等于0 但没关系
OK, but generally this is what we are going to assume
因为通常我们都会假设它成立
in the type of potential function argument
把这些我们用到的势能参数
that we are going to be doing.
假设为符合条件的
OK, so I just want to let you know that there are bigger,
我只是想让你们知道 它很广
there is a bigger space of potential function arguments
势能函数参数的选择范围很广
than the one that I'm showing you here.
并不只是我这里给出的一两个
OK, so then, under this circumstance,
然后在这种假设的前提下
we define the amortized cost c_i hat
定义平摊代价为c^i
with respect to phi as,
对Φ(D_i)有……
and this is one of these formulas that
这一条公式是
if you can't remember it,
如果你不能记住的话
definitely put it down on your crib sheet for the final.
你就必须记在笔记里 注明期末考点
So c_i hat is equal to
c^i等于
c_i plus phi of D_i minus phi of D_i minus one.
c_i加上Φ(D_i)减去Φ(D_(i－1))
So this is the change in potential difference.
这部分是势能的改变量
And, let's call it delta phi i for shorthand.
我们将它简称为△Φ_i
And let's see what it means to have --
让我们看一下这意味着什么——
-- in the different circumstances.
——在不同的环境变量下
So, if delta of phi i is greater than zero,
如果△Φ_i大于0
So if this is greater than zero,
也就是这个大于0
then what's the relationship between c_i hat and c_i?
那么c^i和c_i的关系是什么样的？
This is greater than zero.
它大于0
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Yeah, c_i hat is then greater than c_i, OK?
[教授]:没错 c^i大于c_i
Then, c_i hat is greater than c_i.
那么c^i大于c_i
And what does that mean?
这意味着什么
That means when I do operation I,
意味着当进行操作i时
I charged more than it cost me to do the operation.
我收取的费用 超过了这个操作所需的代价
So, the extra amount that I charged
我多收取的费用
beyond what I actually used is being put into the bank,
超过实际花费部分会存进银行
OK, is being stored as potential energy.
变成势能储存起来
So, op I stores work in the data structure for later.
操作i储存了后面数据结构所需的功
Similarly, if delta phi i is less than zero,
同样的 如果△Φ_i小于0
then c_i hat is less than c_i.
那么c^i小于c_i
And so, the data structure delivers up work --
数据结构要转化出一部分功
——to help pay for op I,
——来帮助支付操作i
OK, for operation I.
付给操作i
So, if it's less than zero,
如果它小于0
that means that my change in potential,
那意味着势能的改变
that means my bank account went down as a result,
意味着银行存款余额变少
and so therefore, what happens was
因此 这种情况下
the data structure provided work to be done in order...
数据结构会提供功来完成操作
because the true cost was bigger than the amortized cost.
因为实际代价大于平摊代价
So, if you think about it,
好 你试想一下
the difference between looking at it from
两种方法的差异是
the potential function point of view
从势能法的角度
versus the accounting point of view,
跟从记帐法的角度比较
the accounting point of view, you sort of say,
用记帐方法来看
here is what my amortized cost will be.
你就会先决定一个平摊代价
Now let me analyze my bank account,
然后再分析一下银行存款
make sure it never went negative.
确保它不为负值
In some sense, in the potential function argument,
在某种程度上 在势能法里
you're saying, here's what my bank account is all the time.
你就会说 我的银行存款是这样子的
Now let me analyze what the amortized costs are.
然后再分析一下 哪个平摊代价才适合
So, that's sort of the difference in approaches.
这是两种方法的不同之处
One is you are sort of specifying the bank account.
一种考虑的是银行存款
The other, you're specifying the amortized costs.
另一种考虑的是平摊代价
So, we look at the,
那我们来看一下
why is it that this is a reasonable way to proceed?
为什么这是一种合理的操作方式
Well, let's look at the total amortized cost of n operations.
看一下n个操作的总的平摊代价
That's just the sum,
这是个求和运算
i equals one to n of c_i hat.
对c^i从1到n求和
That's the total amortized cost.
这是总平摊代价
And that's equal to, but substitution,
它等于 替换一下
just substitute c_i hat for this formula.
将c^i替换成这条公式
So that's c_i plus phi of D_i minus phi of D_i minus one.
等于c_i加上Φ(D_i)减去Φ(D_(i-1))
and that's equal to c_i.
等于∑(i=1到n) c_i
And now, what happens when I sum up these terms?
然后 把这些项加起来会得到什么？
What happens when I sum up these terms?
把这些项加起来会怎样？
What's the mathematical term we use?
用数学术语是怎么说的？
It telescopes.
它是可缩进的
OK, every term on the left
左边的每个项
is added in once when it's I,
当作为第i项时 会加进来一个
and subtract it out when it's I minus one,
作为第i-1项时 会减去一个
except for the first and last terms.
除了第一项和最后一项
The term for n is only added in,
第n项只有加 （但不会减掉）
and the term for zero is only subtracted out.
第0项只有减 （没有加进来）
OK, so that's because it telescopes.
因为这是可缩进的
So this term is what?
所以这一项是多少？
What property do we know of this?
它具有什么已知性质？
It's greater than or equal to zero.
它大于或等于0
And this one equals zero.
这个等于0
So, therefore, this is greater than or equal to c_i.
因此这个大于或等于c_i的总和
And thus, the amortized costs
这样一来 平摊代价
are an upper bound on the true costs, which is what we want.
是实际代价的一个上限 这正是我们想要的
Sum of the amortized costs
平摊代价的总和
is an upper bound up on the sum of the true costs.
是实际代价总和的上限
But here, the way that we define the amortized costs
但这里定义平摊代价的方式
was by first defining the potential function.
是先定义势能函数
OK, so the potential function is sort of, as I said,
所以势能函数就是  正如我所说的
the difference between the accounting and the potential method is,
记帐方法和势能方法的区别是
do you specify the bank account
你考虑的是银行存款
or do you specify the cost?
还是平摊代价？
OK, do you specify the potential energy at any point,
你针对的是任意点的势能
or do you specify the cost at any point?
还是在任意点的代价？
OK, but in any case, you get,
但无论哪种情况 你都能得到
this bound, also this math is nicer math.
这个上限 而同时这是漂亮的数学过程
I like telescopes.
缩进什么的最喜欢了
So the amortized costs upper bound the true costs.
所以 平摊代价是实际代价的上限
OK, let's do table doubling.
好的 做一下表扩增
Over here.
在这里
So, to analyze this, we have to define our potential.
要分析这个 先要定义势
OK, if anybody can guess this off the top of their head,
有谁的第一反应能猜出这是什么
they're better than I am.
那他就比我还要聪明
I struggled with this for probably
你看 我都已经聪明绝顶了
easily a couple hours to get it right,
但还要花几个小时才做出来
OK, because I'm not too smart.
可能因为我的顶太绝了
that's a potential function I'm going to use,
这是所要用到的势能函数
OK, 2i minus two to the ceiling of log i.
2i减去2的log i的上取整次方
And, we're going to assume that
接下来 我们要假设
two to the ceiling of log of zero is equal to zero,
2^┌log 0┐= 0
because that's what it is in the limit.
因为它的极限就是这样
For log of zero, this becomes minus infinity,
对于log 0 等于负无穷
so, two to the minus infinity is zero.
所以2的负无穷次方等于0
So, that's just going to be a mathematical convenience.
这仅仅是为了数学计算上的方便
Assume that. OK, so where did I get this from?
假设是这样 我是怎么推出这条式的？
I played around.
我做了很多尝试
I looked at that sequence that I have erased and I said Ok
我观察了刚擦掉的那个序列
because reversing,
然后通过逆运算
there are some problems for which
其实现在问题是
defining a potential function is fairly easy.
定义一个势能函数并不难
But, defining the amortized costs is hard,
但是定义其平摊代价就很难了
OK, to define the accounting.
或者定义存款
So, for this one, the accounting method is,
所以说 对于这个例子 记账方法
I would say, an easier method to use.
是相对容易的一种方法
However, I'm going to show you that
但我将证明给你看
you still can do it with potential method
你仍能用势能方法来做
if you come up with the right potential.
如果你一开始使用了对的势
So, intuitively, this is basically
直觉上 这也是
what's left in the bank account at the I'th operation
第i步操作时剩余的银行存款
because I've put in 2i things into the bank,
因为我把这些2i 存进了银行
and I've subtracted out this many,
并且 我又减去这些东西
essentially, from table doublings,
本质上 它们是用于表扩增的开销
OK, up to that point, OK?
大概是那个意思
So, first let's observe, what is phi of D_0?
首先要观察Φ(D_0)是多少？
So, that's good.
非常好
And, the phi of D_i is greater than or equal to zero.
Φ(D_i)大于或等于0
Why is that?
为什么会这样？
So, what's the biggest that ceiling of log i could be?
┌log i┐最大可能是多少？
Ceiling of log i is either log i or
┌log i┐或者等于log i
log i quantity plus one, OK?
或者等于log i的值加上1
So, the biggest it is, is log i plus one.
所以最大值是log i + 1
If it's log i plus one,
如果是log i + 1
two to the log i plus one, it's just 2i.
2的log i + 1次方 就是2i
That's the biggest it could be, right?
这是它的最大值 对哇？
Two to log i plus one, is just,
2的（log i + 1）次方
let's do it the other way, is i times two,
换一种算法 就是i乘以2
OK, i for that part, two for that part.
i是这一部分 2是这一部分
OK, so that the biggest it could be.
这是它的最大值了
OK, or it's just log of i.
或者只是log i
So, either this is going to be 2i minus i or 2i minus 2i.
所以这里或者等于2i-i 或者等于2i-2i
In either case, it's bigger than zero
这两种情况都大于0
So, those are the two properties I need for this
所以这两个性质是我需要的
to be a well-defined potential function.
用来定义好的势能函数的性质
Now, that doesn't say that
但现在 这还不能说明
the amortized costs are going to be
这个平摊代价将保证...
satisfied the property that things are going to be cheap,
保证总操作的代价会比较低
that I'm going to be able to do my analysis
并不意味着我只要做做分析
and get the kind of bounds I want.
然后就能得到 我要的上限
But, it sets up to say, yes, I've satisfied
但它至少给出了
the syntax of having a proper potential function.
一个合适的势能函数的规则
So, let's just do a quick example here
举一个简单的例子
just to see what this means.
看一下这些表示着什么
So, imagine that I am in the situation where I have eight,
假设在这种情况下有8个
did I do that right, yeah,
我画对了没有？
OK, eight slots, and say six of them are full.
没错 有8个槽 其中有6个是满的
So then, phi by this is going to be 2i.
那么这个的势能函数值等于 2i
That's two times six minus two to the 2i.
也就是 2乘以6减去 2的2i次方
What's that? Sorry, minus two to the ceiling of log i.
那是多少？不是 是减去2^┌log i┐
So, i is six, right, so log of i is log of six.
i等于6 log i就是log 6
The ceiling of it is three.
上取整等于3
So, that's minus 2^3, which is eight.
所以这是减去2^3 也就是8
So, that's 12 minus eight. That's four.
这样12减去8 得到4
And if you think about this in the accounting method,
如果你用记帐方法想一下
these would be zeros, and these would be twos, right,
这些槽都是0 这些槽是2
for the accounting method if we do the same thing,
如果用记帐方法来分析的话
because this is halfway through, right,
因为这个刚进行到一半
all zeros, and that we add two for each one that we're going in.
所以这些都是0 然后这些槽都加2
So, my function is, in fact, telling me what the actual cost is.
实际上这个函数 告诉了我们实际代价是多少
OK, everybody with me?
大家都明白吗？
So that's what we mean by this particular potential function.
这就是这个特殊的势能函数的含义
So now let's add up the amortized cost of the i'th insert.
现在将第i个插入操作的平摊代价加起来
So that's the amortized cost of the i'th insert,
这是第i个操作的平摊代价
just by definition.
由定义可知
OK, and now that's equal to, well, what is c_i?
现在它等于... c_i是多少？
Do we still have that written down somewhere,
结果还在黑板上吗？
or have we erased that at this point?
还是被我们擦掉了？
I think we erased it.
应该被擦掉了
Well, we can write it down again.
我们可以再写一遍
It is i if i minus one is an exact power of two.
它等于i 如果i-1刚好是2的幂
And, it's one otherwise. That's c_i.
否则它为1 这是c_i
That's this term, plus, and now phi of D_i:
就是这一项 再加上Φ(D_i)
so, what is that?
它是多少？
phi of D_i is this business,
Φ(D_i)等于这个
2i minus two ceiling of log i minus
2i 减去 2^┌log i┐ 再减去
2i minus one minus two ceiling of log of I minus one.
2(i-1)减去2^┌log(i-1)┐
So that's the amortized cost.
这就是平摊代价了
That's a nice, pretty formula, right?
很工整 很漂亮的公式
OK, let's hope it simplifies a little.
再把它简化一下
So that's equal to,
它等于
well, we have the i and the one here, if, etc.,
这里是i和1 如果 这里省略
that business, plus,
就是上面的那坨 再加上
OK, well, we have some things we can cancel here, right?
这里有一些可以抵消的
So in particular, this one we can cancel, right?
尤其是这一项 可以抵消掉
So here, we have 2i minus 2i.
所以这里是2i减去2i
That cancels.
抵消掉
And then we have what's left over here is a minus two.
这里剩下的是负的负2
So, that's a plus two.
负负得正 变成加2
And now, I have minus this term plus this term.
然后再减去这一项 再加上这一项
That's a lot prettier.
这样漂亮多了
OK, it's still a mess.
但还是很乱
We've got to case analysis.
然后我们要分步讨论
Why is it suggestive of a case analysis?
为什么要分步讨论？
We have a case.
因为爱情
So let's do a case analysis.
那么做一下分步讨论吧
OK, so case one, I minus one is an exact power of two.
对于情形1 i-1刚好是2的幂值
So then, c_i hat is equal to, well, c_i is now just i.
那么 c^i等于... 这里c_i是i
That's that case. And then we have the rest there,
在这种情况下 然后写上剩余的公式
plus two, minus two, ceiling of log i
加上2减去2^┌log i┐
minus two ceiling of log of i minus one.
减去2^┌log（i-1）┐
And that's equal to i plus two.
等于i + 2
Well, let's see.
看一下
If I minus one is an exact power of two, what is this term?
如果i-1刚好是2的幂 这一项是多少？
i minus one is an exact power of two.
i-1刚好是2的幂
Plus, thank you, sorry about that.
这里是加 不好意思
It's good to have students, some may say,
有学生真好
because, boy, my math is so bad.
因为我的数学太渣了
This is actually why I end up being a pretty good theoretician
这也是为什么我会成为一个的理论家
because I don't ever trust what I've written down.
因为我连自己写下来的东西都不相信
And so, I write it down in a way that I can verify it
所以 我把它写下来 只是为了可以验证它
because otherwise I just am not smart enough
因为我不够聪明
to carry through five equations in a row and
如果一行里摆了五条算式
expect that everyone is going to be transformed appropriately.
那结果肯定是必有我失
OK, so you write it down.
把它写下来
So I always write it down so I can verify it.
我习惯把它写下来 这样才能够验证它
And that fortunately has the side benefit that
而且这样做还有个被动技能
other people can understand what I've done as well.
就是别人也能理解我所写的内容
so what is this one?
那么 这一项是多少？
This is two to the log of i minus one
它是2^┌log（i-1）┐
because the ceiling,
因为是往上取整
if this is an exact power of two, right,
如果它刚好是2的幂
then ceiling of log of i minus one is just log of i minus one.
那么log（i-1）上取整就是log（i-1）
So, this is two to the log of i minus one,
所以等于2^log（i-1）
which is i minus one,
就是i-1
Right?  Yeah?
这里很不可思议
OK?
没有掌声很不可思议
If it's an exact power of two, then the log is an integer.
如果它刚好是2的幂 那么log的结果就是整数
So, taking the ceiling, it doesn't matter,
所以往上取整并没有影响
get rid of the ceiling.
去掉上限符号
OK, this one, however, is not an exact power of two.
但这一项 并不是2的幂
But what is it?
但它是多少？
It's just one more than this guy.
它只是比这个大1
We know that i minus one is not an exact power of two,
已知i-1不是2的幂
so it's going to be the next bigger one.
那么它就是下一个整数
So that means this is what?
这意味着这是多少
So, it's going to be, how do these two compare?
它就是 这两个比较一下
How much bigger is this one than this one?
这个比这个大多少？
It's twice the size.
是它大小的两倍
We know what this one is.
已知这个值
OK, or it can reason it from first principles.
用基本原理也可以推导出
This is going to be the log of i minus one plus one.
这个是log（i-1）+1
OK, and so then you can reduce it to this.
这样可以推导出这个
So, you've got to think about those floors and ceilings, right?
你们回去要想想 上取整和下取整
It's like, what's happening in the round off there?
它就像是四舍五入
So now we can simplify this.
现在就可以简化了
OK, so what do we have here? We have,
这里能得出什么？ 我们有...
OK, so if I multiply this through,
如果将这些乘出来
I have an i plus two minus 2i plus two plus i minus one.
得出i+2-2i+2+i-1
I know a lot of you, probably 90% of you won't do this step.
我就知道 你们可能有90%的人会跳过这一步
You will go directly from this step to the last step.
你会直接从这一步跳到最后一步
And that's where 30% of you,
而这其中又有30%的人
or some number, will get it wrong.
或多或少会算错
OK, so let me encourage you to do that step.
所以我建议你们都算这一步
OK, it's easier to find your bugs if you take it slow.
如果你们慢一点 你们就更容易发现错误
Actually, taking it slow is faster in the long run.
实际上 慢工出细活
It's hard to teach young stallions,
你们还是很傻很天真
or phillies, or whatever, OK?
又很不熟练
Just take it easy.
悠着点
Just patience, just do it slow, get it right.
耐心地 慢慢地来做 把它做对了
It's actually faster.
这样其实更快
OK, everybody knows the tortoise and hare story.
大家都知道乌龟和兔子的故事吧
Yeah, yeah, yeah, OK, but nobody believes it.
爷爷也~~不相信
OK, so now here we have 2i here,
好的 现在这里是2i
that leaves us with two plus two minus one, equals three.
剩下2+2-1 等于3
Awesome, awesome.
威武霸气
OK, amortized cost is three
平摊代价是3
when i minus one is an exact power of two.
这是i-1刚好是2的幂的情况
OK, case two.
第二种情况
OK, i minus one is not an exact power of two.
i-1不是2的幂
So then we have c_i hat is equal to,
那么c^i等于
now instead of i it's one plus,
现在不是i 而是1 加上
and then the two minus two to the ceiling of log i
然后加上2减去2^┌logi┐
plus two to the ceiling of log of i minus one.
加上2^┌log(i-1)┐
OK, now what can somebody tell me about these two terms
现在有人能告诉我这两项是多少吗
in the case where i minus one is not an exact power of two?
在i-1不是2的幂的情况下
What are they? Equal.
这两个是多少？相等
Why is that?
为什么?
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：……
[Prof]:Yeah, the ceiling is going to do the same thing to both,
[教授]:没有 上取整对这两项效果一样
going to take it up to the same integer.
取为相当的整数
So these two things are equal,
所以这两项相等
which means this is equal to three.
意味着它等于3
So therefore, n inserts,
因此 n个插入
OK, so now I say, oh, the amortized cost is three
现在我知道了 平摊代价是3
for every operation for every insert.
对于每个操作 每个插入都是3
So therefore, n inserts costs, well,
因此 n个插入花费
the amortized cost of each is three.
每一个的平摊代价是3
So n of them, the amortized cost is 3n.
有n个 所以平摊代价是3n
That's an upper bound on the worst-case true costs.
这也是最坏情况下实际代价的上限
So, n inserts costs order n in the worst case.
所以n个插入在最坏情况下代价为θ(n)
OK, there is a bug in this analysis.
但这个分析里有一个漏洞
It's a minor bug.
一个很小的错误
It's the one I pointed out before
我在之前指出来过
the first insert has amortized cost of two, and not three.
第一个插入的平摊代价是2 不是3
I didn't actually deal with that one carefully enough.
实际上 我从没仔细地研究过这个问题
OK, so that's an exercise to just go and look to see
这是一个练习 你们回去研究一下
where it is that that happens and how you show that,
为什么会这样 你要如何证明
in fact, the amortized cost of the first one is two,
实际上 第一项的平摊代价是2
OK, where that shows up.
表现出来是这样
OK, so to summarize, actually let me summarize over here,
总结一下 最后在这里总结一下
conclusions about amortized analysis.
平摊分析的结论
So amortized costs provide a clean abstraction
平摊分析为数据结构的性能
for data structure performance.
提供了一个简洁的抽象概念
So, what I can tell somebody,
我能告诉人们
so suppose I built a dynamic table, for example,
假设我建立一个动态表 打个比方
OK. It's easier to say,
你很容易就能看出来
in terms of your own performance modeling,
根据你自己的性能模型
it costs a constant amount of time for each insert.
每个插入都花费一定量的时间
As long as you don't care about real-time behavior,
只要你不关注实时表现
but only the aggregate behavior,
只关注聚集行为
that's a great abstraction for the performance.
这是一个相当好的性能抽象概念
Rather than saying it's got that complicated thing
虽然某些地方可能会比较复杂
which sometimes cost you a lot,
即有时候代价会很大
how do they reason about that?
你要怎么解释？
But you could say every operation costs me order one,
但你还是能说 每个操作都花费θ(1)
that's really simple.
其实很简单
But they have to understand,
但你要他们理解
it's order one in an amortized sense, OK.
这是从平摊的角度来说的θ(1)
So, if they do have a real-time constraint to make,
如果他们给你一个实时代价的限制
amortized doesn't cut it.
平摊分析就没辙了
but for many problems, it's perfectly good.
但对于很多问题 这方法都是非常好用的
It lets me explain it rather simply.
能够相当简单地进行解释
We will see some other data structures that have amortized costs
你会看到另外一些拥有平摊代价的数据结构
where different operations have different amortized costs.
而且不同的操作会有不同的平摊代价
And the nice thing about that is I just add up,
好消息是 你只要把它们加起来就行了
what's the cost of all my different operations,
所有不同操作的代价是多少?
OK, where there is a different cost for each operation?
每个操作的代价不同在哪里？
Some will be log n. Some will be order one, or whatever.
有一些是log n 有一些是θ(1) 或是其它的
Add them up: that's an upper bound on the true costs.
全部加起来 就是实际代价的上限了
tremendous simplification in abstracting and reasoning about
极大地简化了那些复杂数据结构的
those complicated data structures.
抽象化和合理化
Now, so this is probably, this is huge.
这个很可能 这其实说得很大
OK, abstraction, you know, computer science,
抽象化 对于计算机科学
what we teach you through four years of undergraduate,
在四年的大学生活里教给你的
and another year if you go on to M.Eng.,
如果你读工程硕士的话还会多一年
and then if you get a Ph.D. it's another 15 years
如果你再读博士 可能又要15年
or whatever it takes to get a Ph.D.
反正很多很多年 直到你博士毕业
OK, all you teach about is abstraction:
你所学的所有东西都是抽象化
abstraction, abstraction, abstraction.
抽象化 抽象化 抽象化
So, this is a powerful abstraction: quite good.
所以这就是一个强大的抽象概念 非常好
Now, we learned three methods.
今天我们学习了三种方法
In general, any method can be used.
通常情况下 每一种都可用
You can convert one to the other.
你能从其中一个转换到另外一个
But each has situations
但每一个都有特定的情况
where it is arguably simplest or most precise.
使得它是最简单的或是最精确的
So, any of the methods can be used.
所以 任意一种方法都可用
However, you must learn all of them, OK,
无论如何 你要学会所有方法
because there are going to be some situations where you need one,
因为有些情况 你会需要到其中某一个
where it's better to do one, better to do another.
用这个做可能不错 用另一个做会更好
If you're reading in the literature,
如果你读一下文献
you want to know these different ways of doing it.
你想要知道怎样用不同的方法解决问题
And that means that even though
这也意味着 即使你
you may get really comfortable with accounting,
可能用记帐方法用得更顺手
in an exam, or whatever, I may say
在考试中 或其他场合
solve this with a potential function argument.
要用势能函数方法来解决问题
So, you want to be comfortable with all the methods,
那么 最好就是所有方法你都得心应手
Last point is that,
最后一点是
in fact, different potential functions
实际上 不同的势能函数
or accounting costs may yield different bounds.
或不同的记帐代价可能产生不同的上限
So when you do an amortized analysis,
所以当你在做平摊分析时
there's nothing to say that one set of costs
没有这个代价
is better than another.
会比另个一个好
So, just as an example,
只是举个例子
OK, in any data structure generally that supports delete,
通常任意数据结构都支持删除操作
I can amortize all the deletes against the inserts.
我可以用插入 跟删除进行平摊
So, in general, what I could do is say deletes are free,
通常来说 我都假设删除是免费的
OK, and charge twice as much for each insert.
然后 对每个插入都收取两倍的代价
OK, charging enough when I do the insert
插入时 收取足够多的代价
to amortize it against the delete.
然后 平摊给删除操作
That you could do with an accounting method.
可以用记帐方法来试一下
You can also do it with a potential method,
你也可以用势能方法
the potential, then, being the number of items
而这个势能 实际上就是
that I actually have in my data structure times
数据结构里的元素数量 乘以
the cost of the delete for each of those items.
每一项删除的代价
So the point is that I can allocate costs in different ways.
关键是 我能用不同的方法来分摊代价
Or I could have amortized costs
或者说 平摊的代价
which are equal to the true costs.
它们加起来和实际代价相等
So, there are different ways that I could assign amortized costs.
所有 有很多种不同的方法来分配平摊代价
There is no one way, OK,
不止一种方法
and choosing different ones may yield different bounds.
选择不同的方法 可能会得到不同的上限
It may not, but it may yield different bounds.
可能不会 但也可能有不同的上限
OK, generally it does yield different ones.
通常都会得出不同的上限
OK, next time: an amazing use of potential functions.
下节课会讲到势能函数的一种神奇的用法
OK, the stuff is cool, but let me tell you,
这节课很精彩 但我要剧透下
Wednesday's lecture: amazing.
周三的课 亮瞎了
Amazing the type of analysis we are going to be able to do.
那将是见证奇迹的时刻